a few weeks ago i released two videos on
the general effectiveness of
chemotherapy what happens when you add
fasting to the mix this is a first of a
three video series exploring that very
question
[Music]
for the past 50 years chemotherapy has
been a major medical treatment for a
wide range of cancers its main strategy
has been largely based on targeting
cancer cells by means of dna damage
caused in part by the production of free
radicals although these drugs were first
believed to be quite selective for tumor
cells we now know that normal cells also
experience severe chemotherapy dependent
damage leading to dose limiting side
effects including bone marrow and immune
system suppression fatigue vomiting
diarrhea in some cases even death and if
you do survive the dna damage to normal
cells can even lead to new cancers down
the road
there are cell protecting drugs that
have been tried to reduce the side
effects you can you know pump in higher
chemo doses but these drugs have not
been shown to increase survival in part
because they may also be protecting the
cancer cells
what about instead using
fasting for cellular protection during
cancer treatment fasting may have an
unrecognized role in cancer prevention
and treatment short-term fasting before
and immediately after chemotherapy may
minimize side effects while at the same
time actually make cancer cells
more sensitive to treatment
that's exciting
during nutrient deprivation
healthy cells switch from growth to
maintenance and repair but tumor cells
are unable to slow down their unbridled
growth due to growth promoting mutations
that led them to become cancer cells in
the first place this inability to adapt
to starvation may represent an important
achilles heel for many types of cancer
cells
as a consequence of these differential
responses of healthy versus cancer cells
to short-term fasting chemotherapy
causes more dna damage and cell suicide
in tumor cells while potentially leaving
healthy cells unharmed thus short-term
fasting may protect healthy cells
against the toxic properties of
chemotherapy and render tumor cells more
sensitive or at least that's the theory
let's
test it out
tyrosine kinase inhibitors a
group of chemo drugs that are now the
mainstay of treatment and many types of
cancer let's see them in action
these are petri dishes
filled with cancer cells that have been
dyed pink
two types of lung cancer cells and one
type of colorectal cancer this is the
before
and this
the after exposed to the chemo drugs or
lotinib jafitnib
cryxotinib and rigaraphanin
see how there's less pink
that shows how many cancer cells the
chemo killed off
starve the cells for 24 hours first
though and the drugs work even better
even the starvation alone without the
drugs killed off a bunch of them the
researchers conclude that these tki
drugs that are commonly administrated
for treating solid tumors become
potentiated in their activity by 24
hours of starvation
but that's in a petri dish
similar results were found for breast
cancer and a chemo drug called
doxorubicin here's five days of
unhindered growth of breast cancer in a
petri dish from 150 000 cancer cells to
800 000 in under a week
dripping on a little chemo can knock it
down to around 600 000 but starve those
cells for 48 hours first and the chemo
can completely keep them in check
even the short-term starvation alone can
restrain growth
short-term fasting raises the
possibility that you could get twice the
effect
for half the dose which may be
particularly important for a drug as
toxic as doxorubicin which causes heart
failure in as many as one in three
at higher doses again though these are
just in vitro studies in a petri dish
then researchers moved to mice and found
the same dual benefit less toxic chemo
yet at the same time more effective and
not just by a little a high enough chemo
dose to kill a hundred percent in less
than a week but after being starved for
60 hours after the same dose 100
survived
oh okay that's the toxicity what about
efficacy here's tumor growth
without chemo growth
with chemo and with chemo after
short-term fasting and this translated
into improved survival
interestingly fasting alone appeared to
work as well as the chemo and the same
with radiation unbridled tumor growth
knocked down by radiation therapy and
even more so after the combination of
radiation and alternate day fasting but
alternate day fasting all alone seemed
to do as well as the radiation
okay but that's breast cancer in mice
i'm sure
mickey is thrilled for many but what
about in people we'll explore that
next
[Music]
you